Finding aid to the Phi Kappa Psi Society records CA.MS.00098
Smith College Archives
Phi Kappa Psi Society records
1892-1939
Smith College Archives
Phi Kappa Psi Society.
CA.MS.00098
0.833 linear feet (2 containers)
Phi Kappa Psi was an early literary society founded in 1892 by five members of Alpha Society, the first literary society at Smith College. The collection consists of copies of the society's constitution, song booklets, programs, letters, photographs, publications, and record books.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source Unknown
Biographical / Historical
Phi Kappa Psi came into being in 1892 when five members of Alpha Society, Smith's first literary society, decided to form their own group. According to its constitution, Phi Kappa Psi's purpose was "1) to encourage and help maintain a high grade of scholarship, especially in literary lines, by its requirements for membership and by the literary character of its meetings, 2) by association to bring into more intimate and friendly relations girls who are congenial in aims and interests, and 3) by open meetings to contribute in a general way to the literary interests of Smith College."
Membership was based upon a young woman's scholarship, special talents, and her qualification as a "representative girl." Meetings were held monthly and included the singing of songs and the preparation and production of plays, in addition to the publication of a quarterly magazine. In 1934 Alpha Society and Phi Kappa Psi elected to combine as student interests shifted away from the arts. The new organization, Alpha-Phi Kappa Psi, allowed both societies to endure.
In 1938 Alpha-Phi Kappa Psi adopted a new constitution which limited its membership to thirty students who had distinguished themselves in one or more of the arts. This reflected the Society's ideological shift over the years from "an amusement society," as it was described by an 1883 member, to "an honorary [sic] society which recognizes outstanding creative achievement," as it was described in 1938. Activities of Alpha-Phi Kappa Psi were last recorded in 1968.
Scope and Contents
The materials reflect the entire active life of Phi Kappa Psi, from its inception in 1892 to its amalgamation with Alpha Society in 1934 and beyond. The collection consists of copies of the society's constitution, song booklets, programs, letters, photographs of members and officers, publications, and record books of officers. The items highlight the evolution of a specific organization of students at Smith College through several generations of its members.
Phi Kappa Psi.; Alpha-Phi Kappa Psi.; Smith College--Societies, etc.
- Constitution, 1892-1930 (Box 3010)
- History, 1896-1897 (Box 3010)
- Invitations, Songs, etc, . 1892-1939; undated (Box 3010)
- Photographs, 1894-1916 (Box 3010)
- Programs, 1892-1897; undated (Box 3010)
- Programs, 1898-1904 (Box 3010)
- Programs, 1905-1910 (Box 3010)
- Programs, 1911-1920 (Box 3010)
- Publications, 1892-1893 (Box 3010)
- Executive's Book, 1911-1914 (Box 3011)
- Membership, 1892-1934 (Box 3011)
- Minutes, 1892-1903 (Box 3011)
- Minutes, 1903-1914 (Box 3011)
- Minutes, 1914-1932 (Box 3011)
- Minutes, 1916-1917 (Box 3011)
- President's Book, 1911-1917 (Box 3011)
- Recommendations, 1908-1917 (Box 3011)
- Recommendations, 1908-1917 (Box 3011)
- Records, 1900-1905 (Box 3011)
- Records, 1917-1925 (Box 3011)